today we're gonna try to do this with
the microphone right up next to my mouth
and see what kind of impact that has on
the sound quality so the the topic today
is related to the topic for previous
episode thinking and simulated thinking
but here I'm focused on a different
distinction that I'm going to
characterize as a paradigmatic mind and
liminal mind or the middle consciousness
so so to begin with I want to
characterize a paradigmatic mind the
concept of a paradigm as far as I
personally know comes from a coon who is
discussing us in the context of social
environments particularly specifically
scientific communities and the
frameworks the collectives since making
frameworks were used to describe the
world natural phenomena I'm using it in
a in a different sense I'm using it in
the sense of a the sense making
framework there to give an individual
users to make sense of their environment
so for example if you had a contemporary
physicalist paradigm and you saw an
Apple fall from a tree you might invoke
the notion of gravity to describe what
happened whereas say for example you
maybe had an animist paradigm you might
suspect that maybe the tree was trying
to convey something to you and so the
sense making frameworks these paradigms
stand in between raw perception of the
blooming buzzing confusion of phenomenal
reality and the way we actually well
make sense of what's going on ultimately
for the purposes of making meaning
what's going on and taking actions in
the world now paradigms operate in my my
story with three interrelating
principles the first is the principle of
responsiveness which is to say that the
paradigm exists as I said for the
purpose of making sense of your
environments so that you can then make
meaningful choices and effective choices
in your environment so paradigms emerge
so that you can
bond reality however paradigms also seem
to have two other primary
characteristics one I might call the
principle of conservation which is to
say that paradigms in some sense seek to
change as little as they can possibly
change
so hold state hold as much as possible
unchanging and only change it at the
edges minimally and then this the third
is the principle of minimum dissonance
which is to say that if some kind of
perception shows up some experience
comes in that doesn't make sense in the
paradigm there's something about the way
the years since making framework
operates where what you are experiencing
doesn't make sense this shows up as
dissonance and paradigms need to solve
dissonance but they need to resolve
dissonance also under the principle of
maximum conservation so say for example
for whatever reason you're a particular
paradigm didn't have any room whatsoever
for the notion of a hummingbird and
you're sitting in a park and a
hummingbird flies by well the principle
of dissonance is that something is just
an experience that doesn't make sense
and so this needs to be resolved the
principle of maximum conservation is
that the paradigm will endeavour to find
a way to make sense of this in the least
amount of change and and here things
like self deception and delusion
actually come in quite often now of
course it might be that your paradigm
will change to include the concept of
hummingbird you know and so you've got
the idea of bird and it's not that hard
to extend it to some other time move
bird and then eventually be able to
potentially evolve your paradigm develop
it to be able to include this entirely
new concept of hummingbird
but perhaps the easiest thing to do is
just to maybe supposed to just imagine
that it wasn't in fact real and of
course we know that the human mind is
extraordinarily capable of not
perceiving or at least not being aware
of the fact of perceiving things in the
in the sensory environment and this can
be
happening because it just edits things
out that don't seem to be useful like
see a gorilla walking across and behind
a basketball game I don't if you're
familiar with that particular experiment
or it can erase things that are just
don't make any sense
all here now within the boundaries of
the principle of responsiveness so so
let's say for example you had a paradigm
that whatever reason had a framework
that you were fireproof you could not be
burned and you found yourself in fire
and so all you're now experiencing
dissonance which is to say to your body
your skin is sending you signals that
are the minimum pain in fact being
burned some kind of harm but your
paradigm under the principle of
conservation seeks not to change now
what's gonna happen here is attention
you've got a tension between the
dissonance and the conservation but you
also the tense in tension now with with
responsiveness that to fail to respond
to what's actually happening is a
violation of that principle now here
things can be very complex sometimes the
paradigm for whatever reason has enough
hold on on you on your mind that it
holds and the principle of dissonance is
resolved through a delusion which is to
say no no no this isn't really pain I
don't feel anything and you go to the
delusional path which holds the
conservation of the paradigm but in this
case now because it's fire you'll
eventually run into some critical
threshold say you die so so death is the
the absolute boundary the principle of
responsiveness now of course in most
circumstances there's a meaningful gap
between where the principle conservation
gives up and where you actually die and
of course also in other cases we're
quite familiar with circumstances where
people choose to die rather than change
what they believe that's not at all
uncommon in our environment but when you
find yourself in a circumstance where
the principle of responsiveness has
overcome the principle of conservation
you've now entered into a new location
and this is what I'm calling liminal
mind or liminal consciousness and so the
first thing to keep in mind is that this
space the liminal consciousness is in
fact actually the base this is the
source from which paradigms emerge and
therefore it's also the place to which
paradigms dissolve when when they break
up completely and you know under the
principle of conservation when you find
yourself in a circumstance where reality
is it's quite distinct from the
framework that you're using the ability
to modify your paradigm enough to be
responsive to that level of distinctness
might in fact just not be possible like
that kind of change may not be available
and so it can often be the case that
when confronted with circumstances that
are substantially outside of the scope
or capacity of the paradigm under which
were operating the only valid response
is to in fact drop into liminality now
liminality has itself certain
characteristics when you're in a in a
truly deeply mental space you don't
necessarily even have the capacity to
name the things that you're experiencing
so sense making can become very very
limited and you might be in a part
perceiving something that under a
paradigmatic frame you would call a tree
but in a liminal space you don't have a
name for it you're just experiencing it
and it's raw sensorial and of course
this means you can be quite limited like
your your ability to make sense of and
then make meaningful choices in your
environment in a liminal space can be
very limited
you know beginner's mind and child's
mind is it children are quite liminal
and you know in in many circumstances
this is the best place to be and in fact
quite specifically if you happen to be
very successful your your paramedic
framework has put you in a circumstance
where you're a peak predator of the
local niche you know how to get
you could change the world you could
control your environment then dropping
out of that paradigm is a very
challenging choice and of course this
conundrum is one of the primary
problematics the the people who are
doing the best the the most successful
elites are in many ways the least
capable because it makes the least sense
for them as individuals of dropping out
of their paradigm and dropping into
liminality and yet as we said when it is
in fact the case that your paradigm is
substantially maladaptive to the reality
that you find yourself in that is
exactly what one needs to do I think
it's somewhat obvious why I bring up
this particular concept today because it
is in fact my proposition that
effectively all or at least a
substantial fraction of the enormous ly
successful and effective paradigms that
got us here
you know the 20th century framework
particularly 20th century Western
frameworks aren't adequate to the
reality that we find ourselves in so the
reality that the larger their own
success has given rise to and this is
particularly the case for for experts
all right so if you're a very successful
expert in government or academia or
business and you find yourself really
thoughtfully honestly paying attention
to what's happening and you notice that
your toolkit isn't adequate to what's
going on you might find yourself if
you're healthy dropping into a liminal
space and my recommendation in fact my
my counsel is to allow that liminal
space in fact to to recognize how
important it is to be good at dropping
into and holding that liminal space
because that is the place
which truly innovative new concept and
frameworks can emerge it is the place
where you have the highest degree of
generative creativity and it is
precisely when one finds themself in a
circumstance that your your legacy
toolkit isn't adequate that you need to
go there and be mindful of the reality
that it's gonna feel awkward it's going
to feel vulnerable it's going to feel
weak and you might even find yourself in
circumstances where your social
environment is pushing you and urging
you to drop out of a liminal space and
come back into the cardigan Matic model
where your skillful where you have
command and you know that I think is one
of the biggest things that is facing
people now is the ability to be aware of
the use and importance of the mind and
to be able to honestly and honorably
drop out of no longer adaptive paradigms
into the creative space of liminality so
that we can collaboratively generate a
new toolkit that is adequate to the
circumstances of the reality that we
find ourselves in